[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
today i'm talking to randy shoup he's
the vp of engineering and chief
architect at ebay he was previously the
vp of engineering at wework and stitch
fix and he was also a chief engineer and
distinguished architect at ebay back in
randy welcome back to software
engineering radio this will be your
fifth appearance on this show i'm pretty
sure that's a record
thanks jeremy i'm really excited to come
back i always enjoy listening to and
then also contributing to software
engineering radio back at qcon 2007 you
spoke with marcus walter he's he was the
founder of sc radio and you were talking
about developing ebay's new search
engine at the time and kind of looking
back i wonder if you could talk a little
bit about how ebay was structured back
then maybe organizationally and then we
can talk a little bit about the the tech
stack and that sort of thing oh sure
okay yeah so ebay started in 1995 i just
want to like you know orient everybody
same same as the web same as amazon same
as a bunch of stuff so ebay was actually
almost 10 years old when i joined that
seemingly very old first time so yeah
what was ebay's tech stack like then
so ebay has gone through five
generations of its infrastructure it was
transitioning between the second and the
third when i joined in 2004. so the
first iteration was pierre midyard the
founder three day labor day weekend in
1995 playing around with this new cool
thing called the web
he wasn't intending to build a business
he just was playing around with auctions
and wanted to put up a web page so he
had a pearl back end and every item was
a file and it lived on his little 486
tower or whatever he had at the time so
that wasn't scalable and wasn't meant to
be the second generation of ebay's
architecture was what we called v2
very you know creatively that was a c
plus plus monolith an isapi dll with
essentially well at its worst which grew
to 3.4 million lines of code in that
single dll and basically in a single
class not just in a single like repo or
a single file but in a single class so
that was very unpleasant to work in as
you can imagine ebay had about a
thousand engineers at the time and they
were you know as you can imagine like
really stepping on each other's toes and
not being able to make much forward
progress so starting in i want to call
it 2002 so two years before i joined
they were migrating to the creatively
named v3
and v3s architecture was java
and
you know not microservices but like we
didn't even have that term but it wasn't
even that it was many applications so
actually let me take a step back v2 was
a monolith so like all of ebay's code in
that single dll and like that was buying
and selling and search and everything
and then we had two monster databases a
primary and a backup big
oracle machines on sun hardware that was
bigger you know bigger than
refrigerators and that ran ebay for a
bunch of years
before we changed the upper part of the
stack we chopped up that single
monolithic database into a bunch of
domain specific databases or entity
specific databases right so a set of
databases around users you know sharded
by the user id you can talk about all
that if you want you know items again
sharded by item id transactions charted
by transaction id dot dot dot
i think when i joined it was the several
hundred instances of oracle databases
you know spread around but still that
monolithic front end and then in in 2002
i want to say we started migrating into
that v3 that i was saying okay so that's
a that was a rewrite in java again many
applications so you take the front end
and instead of having it be in one big
unit it was
this ear file if people remember back to
you know those days in java you know 220
different of those so like
here is the you know one of them for the
search
you know one application would be the
search application and it would you know
do all the search related stuff the
handful of pages around search ditto for
you know the buying area ditto for the
you know
checkout area ditto for the selling area
dot dot 220 of those and that was again
domain
vertically sliced domains and then the
relationship between those v3
applications and the databases was a
many-to-many thing so like many applica
many of those applications would
interact with items so they would
interact with those item databases many
of them would interact with users and so
they would interact with the user
databases etc happy to go into as much
gory detail as you want about all that
but like that's what but we were in the
transition period between the v2
monolith to the v3
mini applications in 2004. i'm just
going to pause there and like let me
know where you want to take it
yeah so you were saying that i started
as pearl then it became c plus plus and
that's kind of interesting that you said
it was all in one class right so it's
pretty much yeah wow it's got to be a
gigantic brutal i mean completely brutal
yeah 3.4 million lines of code yeah we
were hitting compiler limits on the
number of methods per class so oh my
gosh i'm scared that i happen to know
that at least at the time microsoft
allowed you 16k
methods per class and we were hitting
that limit so wow not great
it's uh it's just kind of interesting to
think about how do you
walk through that code right you have i
guess you just have this giant file
yeah i mean there were you know
different methods
but yeah it was a big map i mean it was
a monolith it was a you know it's a
spaghetti mess and
you know as you can imagine amazon went
through a really similar thing by the
way so this wasn't super i mean it was
bad but like we weren't the only people
that were making that mistake and just
like amazon where they were they did
like one update a quarter
you know at that period like 2000 we
were doing something really similar like
very very slow you know updates and when
we moved to v3 you know the idea was to
change is much faster and we were very
proud of ourselves starting in 2004 that
we upgraded the whole site every two
weeks and we didn't have to do
the whole site but like
each of those individual applications
that i was mentioning right those 220
applications each of those would roll
out on this bi-weekly cadence
and
they had interdependencies and so we
rolled them out in this dependency order
and anyway lots of lots of complexity
associated with that yeah there you go
the v3 that that was written in java i'm
assuming this was a as a complete
rewrite you didn't use the c plus plus
code at all correct yeah we migrated
page by page
so you know in the transition period
which lasted probably five years there
were
pages you know in the beginning all
pages were served by v2 in the end all
pages are served by v3 and you know over
time you iterate and you like rewrite
and maintain in parallel the v3 version
of xyz page and the v2 version of xyz
page and then when you're ready you
start to you know test out at low
percentages of traffic you know what
would what does v3 look like is it
correct and when it isn't do you go and
fix it but then ultimately you migrate
the traffic over to fully be in the v3
world and then you you know
remove or comment out or whatever the
the code that supported that in the v2
monolith
and then you had mentioned using oracle
databases did you have a set for v2 and
a set for v3 and you were kind of trying
to keep them in great questions thank
you for asking that question no no we
had the databases so again as i
mentioned we had pre-d monolith that's
my that's a technical term pre-broken up
the databases
starting in
let's call it 2000 actually i'm almost
certain that's 2000 because we had a
major site outage in 1999 which
everybody still remembers who was there
at the time it wasn't me or i wasn't
there at the time but you know you can
look it up anyway so yeah starting in
2000 we broke up that monolithic
database into what i was telling you
before those entity aligned databases
again one set for items one set for
users once that for transactions you
know dot dot dot you know those
databases were shared between
v3 using those things and then v sorry
v2 using those things and v3 using those
things and then
you know so we completely decoupled the
rewrite of the database you know kind of
data storage layer from the rewrite of
the application layer if that makes
sense
yeah so so you had v2 that was
connecting to these individual oracle
databases you said like they were for
different types of entities like maybe
for items and users and things like that
but it was a shared database situation
where v2 was connected to the same
database as v3 is that right correct and
also
in v3 even when done different v3
applications were also connecting to the
same database again like anybody who
used the user entity which is a lot
we're connecting to the user suite of
databases and anybody who used the item
entity which again is a lot you know
we're connecting to the item databases
etc so yeah it was this many to many
that's what i was trying to say many to
many relationship between
applications in the v3 world and
databases
okay yeah i think i i got it because
it's easier with a diagram yeah because
when you when you think about services
now
you think of services having
dependencies on other services whereas
in this case you would have multiple
services that rather than talking to a
different service they would all just
talk to the same database they all
needed users so they all needed to
connect to the user's database right
exactly and so i don't want to jump
ahead in this conversation but like the
problems that everybody who's feeling
uncomfortable at the moment you're right
to feel uncomfortable
because that was an unpleasant situation
and microservices or more generally the
idea that individual services would own
their own data and only in the only
interactions to the service would be
through the service interface and not
like behind the services back to the to
the data storage layer that's better
and amazon discovered that you know lots
of people discovered that around that
same early 2000s period and so yeah we
we had that situation at ebay at the
time it was better than it was before
right right it's better than a
monolithic database and a monolithic
application layer but it definitely also
had issues as you can imagine
you know thinking about back to that
time where you're saying it's better
than a monolith what were sort of the
trade-offs of you know you have a
monolith connecting to all these
databases versus you having all these
applications connecting to all these
databases like what were the things that
you gained and what did you lose if that
made sense
yeah well why we did it in the first
place is
like isolation between development teams
right so we're looking for developer
productivity or the phrase we used to
use was feature velocity you know so how
quickly would we be able to move and to
the extent that we could move
independently you know the search team
could move independently from the buying
team which could move independently from
the selling team etc that was what we
were gaining what were we losing you
know when you're in a monolith situation
if there's an issue you know where it is
it's in the monolith
you might not know where in the monolith
but like there's only one place it could
be and so
an issue that one has when you break
things up into smaller units especially
when they have this
you know shared
shared mutable state essentially in the
form of these databases like who changed
that
column what's the deal actually we did
have a solution for that or something
that really helped us which was more
than 20 years ago we had something that
we would now call distributed tracing
where
actually i talked about this way back in
the 2007
thing because it was pretty cool at the
time you know just like the spans one
would create using a modern distributed
tracing you know open telemetry or you
know any of the distributed tracing
vendors just like you would do that we
didn't use the term span but that same
idea where and the goal was the same to
like debug stuff so
every time we were about to make a
database call we would say hey i'm about
to make this data you know we would log
i'm about to make this database call and
then it would happen and then we would
log whether it was successful or not
successful we could see how long it took
etc and so we built our own
you know monitoring system which we
called central application logging or
cal totally proprietary to ebay happy to
talk about whatever gory details you
want to know about that but it was
pretty cool
certainly way back in 2000 it was and
that was our mitigation against the
thing i'm telling you which is you know
when not if
something is weird in the database
we can kind of back up and figure out
where it might have happened or things
are slow what's you know what's the deal
and you know because sometimes the
database is slow for reasons and what
thing is you know from an application
perspective i'm talking to 20 different
databases but things are slow like what
is it and cal helped us to figure out
both elements of that right like
what applications are talking to what
databases and what back-end services and
like debug and diagnose from that
perspective and then for a given
application
what
you know databases and backend services
are you talking to and debug that and
then we had monitors on those things and
we would notice when databases would
there be a lot of errors or where when
database is starting in slower than they
used to be and then we implemented what
people would now call circuit breakers
where we would notice that oh you know
everybody who's trying to talk to
database one two three four
is seeing it slow down i guess one two
three four is
unhappy so
now flip everybody to say don't talk to
one two three four and like just that
kind of stuff you're not going to be
able to
serve but whatever that's better than
stopping everything so i hope that makes
sense like you know so all these all
these like modern resilience techniques
we had our own like proprietary names
for them but you know we we implemented
a lot of them way back when yeah and and
i guess just to contextualize it for the
audience i mean this was back in
no this is 2000 back in 2000 yeah okay
again because we had this sorry to
interrupt you because we had the problem
that we were just talking about where
many applications are talking to many
services and databases and we didn't
know what was going on and so we needed
some visibility into what was going on
sorry go ahead
yeah okay so all the way back in 2000
there's a lot
less services out there like nowadays
you think about so many software as a
service products
if you were building the same thing
today what are some of the services that
people today would just go and say like
oh i'll just i'll just pay for this and
have this company handle it for me you
know that wasn't available then yeah
sure well there were
no essentially no
well there was no cloud cloud didn't
happen until 2006 and there were a few
software as a service vendors like
salesforce existed at the time but they
weren't usable in the way you're
thinking of where i could give you money
and you would operate a
technical or you know technological
software service on my behalf you know
what i mean so we didn't have any of the
monitoring vendors we didn't have any of
the
stuff today so yeah so what would we do
you know to solve that specific problem
today i would as we do today at ebay i
would instrument everything with open
telemetry
because that's generic thank you ben
siegelman and lightstep for starting
that whole open sourcing process of that
thing and getting all the vendors to you
know respect it and then i would shoot
you know for my back end i would choose
one of the very many wonderful you know
distributed tracing vendors of which
there are so many i can't remember but
like lightsabers one honeycomb
dot dot you know there are a bunch of
you know back end distributed tracing
vendors in particular you know for that
what else do you have today is i mean we
could go on for hours on this one but
like
we didn't have distributed logging or we
didn't have like logging vendors you
know so there was no splunk there was no
you know any any of those distributed
log or centralized logging vendors so we
didn't have any of those things we were
like caveman you know we built our own
data centers we racked our own servers
we installed all the os's in them you
know by the way we still do all that
because it's way cheaper for us at our
scale to do that but happy to talk about
that too anyway but yeah no the
people who live in
i don't know this is where you want to
go in 2022
the
software developer has this massive menu
of options you know if you only have a
credit card and it doesn't usually cost
that much you can get a lot of stuff
done
from the cloud vendors from the software
service vendors et cetera et cetera and
none of that existed in 2000. it's
really interesting to think about how
different
i guess the development world is now
like because you mentioned how cloud
wasn't even really a thing until 2006
yeah all these these vendors that people
take for granted none of them existed
and so it just it must have been a very
very different time well every year is
better than the previous year
you know in software every year is you
know so at that time we were really
excited that we had all the tools and
capabilities that that we did have and
also you know you look back from you
know 20 years in the future and you know
it looks caveman
you know from that perspective you know
all those things were cutting edge at
the time what happened really was the
big companies rolled their own everybody
you know everybody built their own data
centers racked their own servers
at least at scale and the best you could
hope for the most you could pay anybody
else to do is rack your servers for you
you know what i mean like there were
external people you know and they still
exist a lot of them you know the rack
spaces you know equinix is a center of
the world like they would you know have
a co-location facility you ask them
please
you know i'd like to buy these specific
machines and please rack these specific
machines for me and connect them up on
the network in this particular way that
was the thing you could pay for but you
pretty much couldn't pay them to put
software on there for you that was your
job and then operating it was also your
job if that makes sense and then
back then would that be where
employees would actually have to go to
the data center and then you know put in
their their windows cd or their linux cd
and you know actually do everything
right there yeah 100 yeah in fact again
anybody who operates data centers i mean
there's more automation but
conceptually
when we run three data centers ourselves
at ebay right now all of our software
runs on them so like we have those
physical data centers we have employees
that
physically work in those things
physically
rack and stack the servers again we're
smarter about it now like we buy a whole
rack we roll the whole rack in and cable
it you know with one big you know chunk
sound as distinct from you know
individual wiring and the networks are
different and better so there's a lot
less like individual stuff but you know
at the end of it but yeah
everybody in quotes everybody at that
time was doing that or paying somebody
to do exactly that right
yeah and it's it's interesting too that
you mentioned that it's still
being done by ebay you said you have
three three data centers
because it seems like now maybe it's
just assumed that someone's using a
cloud service they're using aws or
whatnot
and so oh go ahead well i was going to
riff off what you said how the world has
changed i mean so much right so i've
been you know it's fine you didn't need
to say my whole linkedin but like i used
to work on google cloud so i've been a
cloud vendor at a bunch of previous
companies i've been a cloud consumer
stitch fix and we work in other places
so i'm fully aware you know fully fully
personally aware of all that stuff but
yeah i mean ebay is at the size where it
is actually cost effective
very cost effective can't tell you more
than that for us to operate our own
infrastructure right so you know you no
one would expect if google didn't
operate their own infrastructure nobody
would expect google to use somebody
else's right like that that doesn't make
any economic sense and you know facebook
is in the same category
for a while twitter and paypal have been
in that category so there's like this
clas you know there are the
known hyperscalers right you know the
google amazon microsoft that are like
cloud vendors in addition to consumers
internally of their own their own clouds
and then there's a whole class of other
places that operate their own internal
clouds and quotes but don't offer them
externally and again facebook or meta
you know as one example ebay is another
you know dropbox actually famously
started in the cloud and then found it
was much cheaper for them to operate
their own infrastructure again for the
particular workloads that they had so
yeah there's probably i'm making this up
it's called two dozen around the world
of these
i'm making this term up many
hyperscalers right like self
hyperscalers or something like that and
ebay is in that category
i know this is kind of a you know a big
what if but you were saying how once you
reach a certain scale that's when it
makes sense to move into your own data
center and i'm wondering if ebay
had started more recently like let's say
in the last you know 10 years i wonder
if it would have made sense for it to
start on a public cloud and then move to
you know its own infrastructure after it
got bigger or if you know it really did
make sense to just start with your own
infrastructure from the start oh i'm so
glad you asked that the answer is
obvious but like i'm so glad you asked
that because i love to make this point
no one should ever ever
start by building your own servers and
your own
cloud like
no
you should be so lucky
after
years and years and years that you
outgrow the cloud vendors right it
happens but doesn't happen that often
you know it happens so rarely that
people write articles about it when it
happens you know what i mean like
dropbox is a good example so yes 100
anytime
where i mean 2022 anytime in more than
the last 10 years yeah let's call it
let's call it 2010 2012 right when cloud
had proved itself
many times over anybody who starts since
that time should absolutely start in the
public cloud there's no argument about
it and again
one should be so lucky
that over time you're seeing
successive zeros added to your cloud
bill and it becomes so many zeros that
it makes sense to
shift your focus toward building and
operating your own data centers and i
haven't been part of that transition
i've been the other way
you know at other places where you know
i've migrated from owned data centers
and colos into into public cloud that's
the more common migration and again
there are there are a handful maybe not
even a handful of companies that have
migrated away but when they do they've
done all the math right i mean dropbox
has done some great talks and articles
about about their transition and boy the
math makes sense for them so yeah yeah
and it also seems like maybe it's
for certain types of businesses where
moving off of public cloud makes sense
like you mentioned dropbox where
so much of their business is probably
centered around storage or centered
around you know bandwidth and you know
there's probably certain workloads that
it's like need to leave public cloud
earlier yeah i think that's fair i think
that's an insightful comment again it's
all about the economics at some point
you know it's a big investment to
and it takes years to develop the
internal forget the money that you're
paying people but like just to develop
the internal capabilities they're very
specialized skill sets around building
and operating data centers so like it's
a big deal and
so are there particular classes of
workloads
where you would for the same dollar
figure or whatever migrate earlier or
later i'm sure that that's probably true
and again one can absolutely imagine
well they say dropbox in this example
yeah it's because like they they need to
go direct to the storage and i mean like
they want to remove every middle person
you know from the flow of the bytes that
are coming in to the storage media and
it makes perfect sense for for them and
when i last
understood what they were doing which
was a number of years ago they were
hybrid right so they had they had
completely you know they kept the top
you know external layer in public cloud
and then the the storage layer was all
custom i don't know what they do today
but people could check and kind of
coming back to your first time at ebay
is there anything you felt that
you would have done differently
with the knowledge you have now but with
the technology that existed then gosh
that's the 2020 hindsight the one that
comes to mind
is the one we touched on a little bit
but i'll say it more starkly if i could
go back in time
20 years
and say hey we're about to do this v3
transition at ebay i would have
had us move directly to what we would
now call microservices in the sense that
individual services own their own
data storage and are only
interacted with through the public
interface there's a famous amazon memo
around that same time so amazon did the
transition from a monolith into what we
would now call microservices over about
a four five year period 2000 to 2005 and
there's a famous jeff bezos memo from
the early part of that where you know
seven you know requirements i can't
remember them but the sen you know
essentially it was you may never talk to
anybody else's database you may only
interact with other services through
their public interfaces i don't care
what those public interfaces are so they
didn't standardize around corba or
json or grpc which didn't exist at the
time you know like they didn't
standardize around any any particular
interaction mechanism but you did need
to
again have this kind of micro service
capability that's modern terminology
where you know services own their own
data and nobody can talk in the back
door so that is the one architectural
thing that i wish
you know with 2020 hindsight that i
would bring back in my time travel to 20
years ago because that does help a lot
and to be fair amazon was pioneering in
that approach and a lot of people
internally and externally from amazon
i'm told didn't think it would work and
it did famously so that's that's the
thing i would do yeah
i'm glad you brought that up because
when you had mentioned that i think you
said there were 220 applications or
something like that
at certain scales people might think
like oh that sounds like micro services
to me but
when you you mentioned that microservice
to you means it having its own data
store i think that's a good distinction
to bring up yeah so i talk a lot about
microservices that have for for a decade
or so yeah i mean several of the
distinguishing characteristics are the
micro in microservices is size and scope
of the interface right so you can have a
service oriented architecture with one
big service or some very small number of
very large services but the micro in
microservice means this thing does
maybe doesn't have one operation but it
doesn't have a thousand and the several
or the handful or several handfuls of
operations are all about this one
particular thing so that's the one part
of it and then the other part of it that
is critical to the success of that
is owning your own data storage so each
service
you know again
it's hard to do this with a diagram but
like imagine the bubble of the service
surrounding the data storage right so
like people anybody from the outside
whether they're interacting
synchronously asynchronously messaging
synchronous whatever http doesn't matter
are only interacting
to the bubble and never getting inside
where the data is i hope that makes
sense
yeah i mean i mean it's kind of in
direct contrast to before you're talking
about how you had all these databases
that all these services shared so it was
probably hard to kind of keep track of
who had modified data you know one
service could modify it then another
service could get data out and it's been
changed but it didn't change it so it
could be kind of hard to track what's
going on yeah exactly
integration at the database level is
something that people have been doing
since
probably the 1980s and so again i
you know in retrospect it looks like
caveman approach it was pretty advanced
at the time actually even the idea of
sharding of you know hey
there are users and the users live in
databases but they don't all live in the
same one they live in 10 different
databases they're 20 different databases
and then there's this layer that you
know for this particular user it figures
out which of the 20 databases it's in
and finds it and gets it back and you
know that was all pretty advanced and by
the way that's all those capabilities
still exist they're just hidden from
everybody
behind you know nice simple uh software
as a service interfaces anyway but that
takes nothing away from your excellent
point which is yeah it's you know when
you're again when there is this
many-to-many relationship between
applications and databases and there's
shared mutable state
in those databases that that is shared
like that's bad you know it's not bad to
have state it's not bad to have a
mutable state it's bad to have shared
beautiful state
yeah and i i think anybody who's kind of
interested in learning more about the
you had talked about charting and things
like that if they go back and listen to
your your first appearance on software
engineering radio yeah it kind of struck
me how you were talking about sharding
and and how it was something that was
kind of unique or unusual whereas today
it feels like it's very i don't know
quaint is the right word but it's like
it's something that that people kind of
are accustomed to now yeah it seems
obvious in retrospect yeah you know at
the time and by the way ebay didn't
invent sharding as i said in 2007 you
know google and yahoo and amazon and you
know it was the obvious took a while to
reach it but it's one of those things
where once once
people have the
you know brainwave to see oh you know
what we don't actually have to store
this in one database we can we can chop
that database up into
you know into chunks and that looks
similar to each that are self-similar
that was reinvented by lots of the big
companies at the same like time again
because everybody was solving that same
problem at the same time but yeah when
you look back and and you i mean like
and by honestly like everything that i
said there it's still like those all the
techniques about how you shard things
and there's lots of you know it's not
interesting anymore because the problems
have been solved but all those solutions
are still the solutions if that makes
any sense
that you know yeah for sure i mean i
think anybody who goes back and listens
to it yeah like you said it's it's it's
very interesting because it's
it all still applies and it's like
i think the the solutions that are kind
of interesting to me are ones where it's
it's things that could have been
implemented long ago but we just
later on realized like this is how we
could do it well part of it is
as we grow as an industry we discover
new problems you know we get to the
point where you know sharding over
databases is only a problem when one
database doesn't work
you know when it when you're the load
that you put on that database is too big
or you want the availability of you know
multiple and so that's not a day one
problem right that's a day two
or day 2000 kind of problem right and so
a lot of these things yeah well you know
it's software so like we could have done
we could have done any of these things
in older languages and older operating
systems and with older technology but
for the most part we didn't have those
problems or we didn't have them at
sufficiently
enough people didn't have the problem
for us to have solved it as an industry
if that makes any sense you know yeah no
that's a good point because you think
about when amazon first started and it
was just a bookstore right and the
number of people using the site were who
knows it was it might have been tens a
day or hundreds a day i don't i don't
know and and so like you said the
problems that amazon has now in terms of
scale are just like it's a completely
different world than when they started
yeah i mean probably
i'm making it up but i don't think it's
too off to say that it's a billion times
more their problems are a billion-fold
you know what they what they were the
next thing i'd like to talk about is
you
came back to ebay i think about this has
it been about two years ago two years
yeah yeah and so tell me about the
experience of coming back to an
organization that you had been at you
know ten years prior or however long it
was like how is your onboarding
different when it's somewhere you've
been before
yeah sure so um
like you said i worked at ebay from 2004
to 2011 and i worked in a different role
than i have today i'm worked mostly on
ebay search engine and then i left to
co-found a startup which
was in the 99 instead of the one you
know like didn't really do much i worked
at google in the early days of google
cloud as i mentioned on google app
engine and had a bunch of other roles
including more recently like you said
stitch fix and wework leading those
engineering teams and so yeah coming
back to ebay as chief architect and you
know leading the
developer platform essentially part of
ebay yeah what was the onboarding like i
mean
lots of things had changed you know in
the in the intervening 10 years or so
and lots had stayed the same you know
not in a bad way but just you know some
of the technologies that we use today
are still some of the technologies we
used 10 years ago a lot has changed
though a bunch of the people are still
around so there's something about ebay
that people tend to stay a long time you
know it's not really very strange for
people to be at ebay for 20 years in my
particular team of let's call it 150
there are four or five people that have
crossed their 20-year anniversary at the
company and i rejoined with a bunch of
other
boomerangs as the term we use
internally so it's you know including
the ceo by the way so sort of bringing
the band back together a bunch of people
that had gone off and worked at it but
at other places have have come back for
various reasons over the last couple of
years so it was both a lot of
familiarity a lot of unfamiliarity a lot
of familiar faces yeah
so
i mean having these people who you work
with still be there and actually coming
back with some of those people
what were some of the big i guess
advantages or benefits you got from you
know those existing connections yeah
well i mean as with all things you know
imagine i mean everybody can imagine
like getting back together with friends
that they had from high school or
university or like you had some people
had some schooling at some point and
like you get back together with those
friends and there's this you know
there's this implicit trust in most
situations of you know because you went
through a bunch of stuff together and
you knew each other you know a long time
ago and so that definitely helps you
know when you're returning to a place
where again there are a lot of familiar
faces where there's a lot of trust built
up and then it's also helpful you know
ebay is a pretty complicated place and
it's 10 years ago it was too big to hold
in any one person's head and it's even
harder to hold it in one person's head
now but to be able to come back and have
a little bit of that well more than a
little bit of that context about okay
here's how ebay works and here you know
here are the
you know unique complexities of the
marketplace because it's very unique you
know in the world and so yeah i mean it
was helpful it's helpful a lot and then
also you know in my current role
my main goal actually is to just make
all of ebay better you know so we have
about 4 000 engineers and you know my
team's job is to make all of them
better and more productive and more
successful and being able to combine
knowing the context about ebay and
having a bunch of connections to the
people that you know a bunch of the
leaders here combining that with 10
years of experience doing other things
at other places you know that's helpful
because you know now
there are things that we do at ebay that
okay well there are you know you know
that this other place is doing this has
that same problem and is solving it in a
different way and so maybe we should you
know look into that option so
so you mentioned just trying to make
developers work or lives easier you
start the job how do you decide what to
tackle first like how do you figure out
where the problems are or
what to do next yeah that's a great
question so
again my i lead this thing that we
internally call the velocity initiative
which is about just making
giving us the ability to deliver
features and bug fixes more quickly to
customers right and so for that problem
how can we deliver things more quickly
to customers and improve you know get
more customer value and business value
what i did with in collaboration with a
bunch of people
is what one would call a value stream
map and that's a term from lean
software and lean manufacturing where
you just look end to end at a process
and like say all the steps
and how long those steps take so a value
stream as you can imagine like all these
steps that are
happening at the end there's some value
right like we've produced some you know
feature or you know hopefully gotten
some revenue or like helped out the
customer the business in some way and so
a value you know mapping that value
stream that's what it means and when you
can see the end-to-end process you know
and like really see it in some kind of
diagram you can look for opportunities
like oh okay well you know if it takes
us i'm making this up it takes us a week
from
when we have an idea to when it shows up
on the site well you know some of those
steps take five minutes that's not worth
optimizing but some of those steps take
you know five days and that is worth
optimizing and so
getting some visibility into the system
you know looking end-to-end with some
with a kind of view of the system
systems thinking that will give you the
knowledge about or the opportunities
about you know what can be improved and
so that's that's what we did and we
didn't talk with all four thousand
engineers or all you know whatever half
a thousand teams or whatever we had but
we sampled a few and after we talked
with three teams we were already hearing
a bunch of the same things you know so
we were hearing
uh in the whole product life cycle which
i like to divide into four stages i'd
like to say there's planning how does an
idea become a project or a thing that
people work on
software development how does a project
or become committed code software
delivery how does committed code become
a feature that people actually use and
then what i call post release iteration
which is okay it's now they're out there
on the site and we're turning it on and
off for individual users we're learning
in analytics and usage in the real world
and and experimenting and so there were
opportunities at ebay at all four of
those stages which i'm happy to talk
about but what we ended up seeing
again and again
is that that software delivery part was
our current bottleneck so again that's
the
how long does it take from an engineer
when she commits her code to it shows up
as a feature on the site and you know
you know two years ago before we started
the work that i've been doing for the
last two years with a bunch of people on
average at ebay was like a week and a
half so you know be a week and a half
between when someone's finished and then
okay it gets code reviewed and you know
dot dot it gets rolled out it gets
tested you know all that stuff it was
you know essentially 10 days
now for the teams that we've been
working with it's down to two so we used
a lot of
what
people may be familiar with the
accelerate book so it's called
accelerate by nicole forsgren jez humble
and gene kim 2018. like if there's one
book anybody should read about software
engineering it's that
so please read accelerate it summarizes
almost a decade of research from the
state of devops reports which the three
people that i mentioned led so nicole
forsgren you know is a doctor you know
she's a phd in data science she knows
how to do all this stuff anyway so when
your problem happens to be software
delivery the accelerate book tells you
all the kind of continuous delivery
techniques trunk based development all
sorts of stuff that you can do to to
solve those problems and then there are
also four metrics that they use to
measure the effectiveness of an
organization software delivery so people
might be familiar with deployment
frequency how often are we deploying a
particular application
lead time for change that's that time
from when a developer commits our code
to when it shows up on the site change
failure rate which is when we deploy
code how often do we roll it back or
hotfix it or you know there's some
problem that we need to you know address
and then i mean time to restore which is
when we have one of those
incidents or problems how quickly can we
roll it back or do that hotfix and again
the beauty of nicole forsgren's research
summarized in the accelerate book is
that the science shows that companies
cluster in other words mostly the
organizations that are not good at you
know deployment frequency and lead time
are also not good at the quality metrics
of
mean time to restore and change failure
rate and the companies that are
excellent at you know deployment
frequency and lead time are also
excellent at mean time to recover and
change failure rate so companies or
organizations divide into these four
categories so there's low performers
medium performers high performers and
then elite performers and ebay on
average at the time and still on average
is solidly in that medium performer
category
so and what we've been able to do with
the teams that we've been working with
is we've been able to move those teams
to the high category so just super
briefly and i will give you a chance to
ask you some more questions but like in
the low category all those things are
kind of measured in months right so how
long how often are we deploying you know
measure that in months how long does it
take us to get a commit to the site you
know measure that in months and then the
low performer sorry the medium
performers are like everything's
measured in weeks right so like it we
would deploy you know a couple you know
once every couple weeks or once a week
lead time is you know measured in weeks
etc the high performers things are
measured in days and the elite
performers things are measured in hours
and so you can see there's like order of
magnitude improvements when you go from
you know when you move from one of those
kind of clusters to another cluster
anyway so what we were focused on again
because our problem with software
delivery was moving the whole set of
teams from that medium performer
category where things are measured in
weeks to the high performer category
where things are measured in days
throughout all this you said the the big
thing that you focused on was the
delivery time so somebody
wrote code and they felt that they was
ready for deployment but for some reason
it took 10 days to actually get out to
the actual site so i wonder if you could
talk a little bit about maybe a specific
team or a specific application where
where was that time being spent you know
you you said you moved from 10 days to
two days what was happening in the
meantime yeah no that's a great question
thank you yeah so okay so now we looked
end to end at the process and we found
that software delivery was the first
place to focus and then there are other
issues in other areas but we'll get to
them later so then to improve software
delivery now we asked individual teams
we did something like um you know some
conversation like i'm about to say so we
said hi
it looks like you're deploying kind of
once or twice a month if i told you you
had to deploy
once a day tell me all the reasons why
that's not going to work and the teams
are like oh of course well it's a build
times take too long and the deployments
aren't automated and you know our
testing is flaky so we have to retry it
all the time and you know dot dot dot
dot and we said great you just gave my
team our backlog right so rather than
you know just coming and like let's
complain about it which the teams were
it's legit for them to complain you know
we were able because again the developer
program or sorry the developer platform
you know is part of my team we said
great like you just gave us you just
told us all the all your top issues or
your impediments as we say and we're
gonna work on them with you and so every
time we had some idea about well i bet
we can use canary deployments to
automate the deployment which we have
now done we would pilot that with a
bunch of teams we'd learn
what works and doesn't work and then we
would roll that out to everybody so what
were the impediments it was a little bit
different for each individual team but
in some it was the things we ended up
focusing on or have been focusing on are
build times you know so we build
everything in java still and even though
we're generation five as opposed to that
generation three that i mentioned still
build times for a lot of applications
were taking way too long and so we we
spent a bunch of time improving those
things and we were able to take stuff
from you know hours down to you know
single digit minutes so that's a huge
improvement to developer productivity we
made a lot of investment in our
continuous delivery pipelines so making
all the automation around you know
deploying something to one environment
and checking it there then deploying it
into a common staging environment and
checking it there and then deploying it
from there into the production
environment and then you know rolling it
out via this canary mechanism
we invested a lot in something that we
call traffic mirroring which we didn't
invent but other places have a different
name for this i don't know if there's a
standard industry name some people call
it shadowing but the idea is i have a
change that i'm making which is not
intended to change the behavior like
lots of changes that we make bug fixes
etc upgrading to new you know open
source dependencies whatever changing
the version of the framework there's a
bunch of changes that we make regularly
day to day as developers which are like
refactorings kind of where we're not
actually intending to change the
behavior
and so traffic mirroring was our idea of
you have the old code that's running in
production and you fire a production
request at that old code and it responds
but then you also fire that request at
the new version and compare the results
you know did the same json come back you
know between the old version and the new
version that's a great way kind of from
the outside to sort of black box detect
any unintended changes in the behavior
and so we definitely leveraged that very
very aggressively we've invested in a
bunch of other things but all those
investments are driven by what do the
particular teams tell us
are getting in their way and there are a
bunch of things that the teams
themselves have you know been motivated
to do so my team's not the only one
that's making improvements you know
teams have moved from branching
development to trunk based development
which makes a big difference making sure
that pr approvals and like you know code
reviews are happening much more
regularly so like right after a thing
that some teams have started doing is
like immediately after stand up in the
morning everybody does all the code
reviews that you know are waiting and so
things don't drag on for you know two
three days because whatever so there's
just like a you know everybody kind of
works on that much more quickly teams
are building their own automations for
things like testing site speed and
accessibility and all sorts of stuff so
like all the things that you know
a team goes through in the development
and roll out of their software we've
been spending a lot of time automating
and making leaner making more efficient
so some of those it sounds like the the
pr example is really
on the team like you're telling them
like hey this is something that you
internally should change how you work
for things like improving the build time
and things like that did you have like a
separate team that was helping these
teams you know speed that process up or
what was that like yeah great i mean you
give give to those two examples are are
like you say very different so i'm going
to start from we just simply
showed everybody here's your deployment
frequency for this application here's
your lead time for this application
here's your change failure rate and
here's your mean time to restore and
again as i didn't mention before
all the state of devops research and the
accelerate book prove that by improving
those metrics you get better engineering
outcomes and you also get better
business outcomes so like it's
scientifically proven that improving
those four things matters okay so now
we've shown to teams hey we would like
you to improve you know for your own
good
but you know more broadly at ebay we
would like the deployment frequency to
be
faster and we would like the lead time
to be shorter and the insight there is
when we deploy smaller units of work
when we don't like batch up a week's
worth of work a month's worth of work
much less risky to just deploy like an
hour's worth of work and the insight is
the hour's worth of work fits in your
head and if you roll it out and there's
an issue
first off rolling back is no big deal
because you've only lost an hour of work
for a temporary period of time but also
like you never have this thing like what
in the world broke because like with a
month's worth of work there's a lot of
things that changed and a lot of stuff
that could break but with an hour's
worth of work it's only like one change
that you made so you know if something
happens like it's pretty much pretty
much guaranteed to to be that thing
anyway that's the backstory and so yeah
then we were just working with
individual teams oh yeah so they were
the teams were motivated
to like
see what's the biggest bang for the buck
in order to improve those things like
how can we improve those things and
again some teams were saying well you
know what a huge component of our of
that lead time between when somebody
commits and it's it's a feature on the
site a huge percentage of that maybe
multiple days is like waiting for
somebody to code review okay great we
can just change our team kind of
agreements and our team behavior to make
that happen and then yes to answer your
question about
were the other things like
building the canary capability and
traffic mirroring and build time
improvements those were done by central
platform and infrastructure teams you
know some of which were in my group and
some of which are in peer peer groups in
my part of the organization so yeah so i
mean like
providing the generic tools and you know
generic capabilities those are
absolutely things that a platform
organization does like that's our job
you know we did it and then there are a
bunch of other things like that around
kind of team behavior and how you
approach building a particular
application that are are and should be
completely in the control of the
individual teams and we're trying not to
be not trying not to be we were
definitely not being super prescriptive
like we didn't come in and say by next
tuesday we want you to be doing trunk
based development by you know the
tuesday after that we wanted to see test
driven development you know dot dot dot
we would just offer to teams you know
here's where you are here's where we
know you can get because like we work
with other teams and we've seen that
they can get there you know they just
work together on well what's the biggest
bang for the buck and and what would be
most helpful for that team so it's like
a menu of options and you don't have to
take everything off the menu if that
makes sense
and how did that communication flow from
you and your team down to
the individual contributor like you have
i'm assuming you have engineering
managers and technical leads and all
these people
sort of in the chain how does it
actually yeah thanks for asking that
yeah i didn't really say how we work as
an initiative so every so there are a
bunch of teams that are involved and we
have every monday morning
just so happens it's late monday morning
today so we already did this a couple
hours ago but once a week we get all the
teams that are involved both like the
platform kind of provider teams and also
the
product or we would say domain like
consumer teams and we do a quick scrum
of scrums like a big old kind of
stand-up what have you all done this
week what are you working on next week
what are you blocked by kind of idea
and you know there are probably 20 or 30
teams again across the individual
platform capabilities and across the
teams that you know consume this stuff
and everybody gives a quick update and
it's a great opportunity for people to
say oh i have that same problem too
maybe we should offline try to figure
out how to solve that together or you
built a tool that automates the site
speed stuff that's great i would i would
so love to have that and so this weekly
meeting has been a great opportunity for
us to share
wins share you know help that people
need and then get teams to help with
each other and also
similarly one of the platform teams
would say something like hey we're about
to you know be done or
beta let's say you know of this new
canary capability i'm making this up
anybody want to pilot that for us and
then you get a bunch of hands raised of
oh we would be very happy to pilot that
that would be great so that's how we
communicate back and forth and you know
it's kind of like engineering managers
are the kind of level that are involved
in that typically so it's not individual
developers but it's like somebody on
most every team if that makes any sense
so like that's kind of how we do that
like communication back to the
individual developers if that makes
sense
yeah so it sounds like you would have
like you said the engineering manager go
to the stand-up and you said maybe 20 to
teams or like i'm just trying to get a
picture for how many people are in this
meeting yeah it's like 30 or 40 people
okay yeah yeah and again it's quick
right it's an hour so we just go boom
boom boom boom and we've just developed
a cadence of people like we have a
shared google doc and like people like
write their little
summaries you know of what they're
what they've worked on and what they're
working on so we've over time made it so
that it's pretty efficient with people's
time and pretty pretty dense in a good
way of like information flow back and
forth and then also separately we meet
more in more detail with the individual
teams that are involved again try to
elicit okay now here's where you are
please let us know what problems you're
seeing with you know this part of the
infrastructure or problems you're seeing
in the pipelines or something like that
and we're you know we're constantly
trying to learn and get better and you
know solicit feedback from teams on what
we can do differently earlier you had
talked a little bit about how
there were a few services that got
brought over from v2 or v3 basically
kind of more legacy or older services
that are have been a part of ebay for
quite some time
and i was wondering if there were things
about those services that
made this process different like you
know
in terms of how often you could deploy
or
just what were some key differences
between something that was made recently
versus something that has been with the
company for a long time yeah sure i mean
the stuff that's been with the company
for a long time was best in class as of
when we built it you know maybe 15 or
sometimes 20 years ago um they're
actually even less than a handful there
are as we speak
there are two or three of those v3
clusters or applications or services
still around and they should be gone and
completely migrated away from in the
next couple of months so like we're
almost at the end of moving all to more
modern things but yeah you know i mean
again stuff that was
state of the art you know 20 years ago
which was like deploying things once
every two weeks like that was a big deal
in 2000 or 2004 and it's you know
like that was fast in 2004 and is slow
in 2022 so yeah i mean what's the
difference
yeah i mean a lot of these things you
know if they haven't already been
migrated there's a reason
and it's because often that they're
way in the guts of something that's
really important you know this is the
this is a core part of i'm making these
examples up and they're not even right
but like it's a core part of the
payments flow it's a core part of
you know how
sellers get paid and those aren't
examples we have those are modern but
you see what i'm saying like stuff
that's like really core to the business
and that's why it's kind of lasted and
i'm kind of curious from the perspective
of some of these new things you're
introducing like you're talking about
improving continuous delivery and things
like that when you're
working with
some of these services that have been
around a long time are the
the teams the rate at which they deploy
or the rate at which you find defects is
that
noticeably different from
services that are more recent yeah
absolutely i mean and that's true of any
legacy at any at any place right so
yeah i mean
people are legitimately
have some trepidation let's say about
you know changing something that's you
know been running the business for a
long long time and so you know it's a
lot slower going
exactly because it's not always
completely obvious what you know what
the implications are of those changes so
you know we were very careful and we you
know test things a whole lot and you
know maybe we didn't write stuff with a
whole bunch of automated tests in the
beginning and so there's a lot of manual
stuff there you know this is just what
happens when you have a company that's
you know been around for a long time
yeah i guess just just kind of to to
start wrapping up as this process of you
coming into the company and and
identifying where the problems are and
working on like you know ways to speed
up delivery
is there is there anything that kind of
came up that really
surprised you i mean you've been at a
lot of different organizations is there
anything about your experience here at
ebay that was very different than what
you'd seen before
no i mean it's a great question i don't
think
i mean i think the thing that's
surprising is how unsurprising it is
like there's not
you know the details are different like
okay you know we have this v3 i mean
like
you know we have some uniquenesses
around ebay but i think what is maybe
pleasantly surprising is all the
techniques about how one might notice
the things that are going on in terms of
you know again deployment frequency lead
time etc and what techniques you would
deploy to like make those things better
all the standard stuff applies you know
so again all the techniques that are
mentioned in the state of devops
research and accelerate and just all the
known
good practices of software development
they all apply
everywhere i think that's the wonderful
thing so like maybe the most surprising
thing is how unsurprising or how
applicable the you know the standard
industry standard techniques are i
certainly hope that to be true but
that's why we i didn't really say but we
piloted this stuff with a small number
of teams exactly because you know we
thought and it turned out to be true
that they applied but we weren't
entirely sure you know we didn't know
what we didn't know and we also needed
proof points you know
not just out there in the world but at
ebay that these things made a difference
and turns out they do so yeah i mean i
think it's easy for people to kind of
get caught up and think like my problem
is unique or my organization is unique
and but it but it sounds like in a lot
of cases maybe we're not so not so
different i mean the stuff that works
tends to work
there's always some detail but yeah i
mean all aspects of you know the
continuous delivery and kind of lean
approach the software i mean
we the industry have yet to find a place
where they don't work seriously you have
to find any place where they don't work
if people want to you know learn more
about the work that you're doing at ebay
or just follow you in general where
should they head yeah so i tweet summary
regularly at
randy shoup so my name all one word
r-a-n-d-y s-h-o-u-p i always wanted to
be a blogger like there's randy shop.com
and there are some blogs on there but
they're pretty old someday i hope to be
doing more writing i do a lot of
conference speaking though so i speak at
the q con conferences i'm going to be at
the craft conf in budapest in a week and
a half as of this recording so you can
often find me on twitter or on software
conferences
all right randy well thank you so much
for coming back on software engineering
radio thanks for having me jeremy it's
fun this has been jeremy jung for
software engineering radio thanks for
listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening